Register of the Nicaraguan Subject Collection, 1927-1998
Hoover Institution Archives
Nicaraguan subject collection,
1927-1998
89002
13 manuscript boxes, 1 oversize box, 2 phonorecords (6.4 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Reports, correspondence, policy statements, speeches, election campaign literature, bulletins, newsletters, pamphlets, serial issues, other printed matter, and audiovisual materials, relating primarily to conditions in Nicaragua since the revolution of 1979, policies of the Sandinista government, human rights issues in Nicaragua, policies of opposition parties in Nicaragua and in exile, and elections in Nicaragua.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1989.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Access Points
Nicaragua.; Nicaragua--Politics and government.; Civil rights--Nicaragua.; Guerrillas--Nicaragua.; Frente Sandinista de Liberacion Nacional.; Elections--Nicaragua.; Phonorecords.; Video tapes.
Series Description
- Subject File, 1927-1992 (Boxes 1-10)
  Reports, correspondence, policy statements, memoranda, election material, bulletins, serial issues, newsletters, flyers, circulars, speeches, clippings, meeting material, press releases, declarations, pamphlets, cartoons, leaflets, statutes, treaty texts, bibliography, inteviews, and miscellany. Arranged alphabetically by subject.
- Oversize File, 1979-1990 (Box 11)
  Newsletters, poem, calendars, oversize pamphlet, flyers, and stamp
- Audiovisual File, 1986-1989 (Box 12, Record cabinet)
  Ten videotape cassettes relating to opposition activities and two phonorecords
Container List
*See card catalog for increments that may have been received since December 1994
- SUBJECT FILE, 1927-1992
  - General. Reports, newsletters, pamphlets, letters, flyers, speeches, serial issues, policy statements, election, clippings, memoranda, bibliography, interviews, bulletins, press releases, leaflets, and miscellany; includes material relating to agriculture, economics, politics, refugees, education, human rights, and the Confederacion Sandinista de Trabajadores. NOTE: General material relating to the Nicaraguan government post- 1979 has been included here; more specific material alluding to or generated by the Frente Sandinista de Liberacion Nacional (as a political party) has been organized under that heading.
    - 1927-1970. Includes a letter by Augusto Sandino (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - 1978-1982 (Folder 2-6)
    - 1984-1986 (Box 2, Folder 1-4)
    - 1987-1989 (Box 3, Folder 1-4)
    - 1989-1991 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Coordinadora Democratica Nicaraguense. Policy statements, reports, declarations, reports, circulars, press release, and ephemera, 1987-1988 (Folder 2)
  - Elections
    - 1984. Reports, bulletins, and guidelines, 1984 (Folder 3)
    - 1990. Pamphlets, flyers, position statements and platforms, reports, leaflets, printed articles, and miscellany, 1989-1990 (Folder 4-5)
      - 1990 (Box 5, Folder 1-2)
  - Europe. Newsletter, reports, flyers, and a postcard; primarily relates to solidarity with the Sandinistas, 1981-1988 (Folder 3)
  - Frente Sandinista de Liberacion Nacional. Policy statements and planning documents, reports, speeches (Daniel Ortega), flyers, bulletins, circulars, cartoons, pamphlets, serial issues, election material, and ephemera
    - Undated (Folder 4)
    - 1978-1983 (Folder 5-7)
    - 1984-1989 (Box 6, Folder 1-3)
  - Human rights
    - General. Reports, flyer, statement, and pamphlets, 1977-1990 (Folder 4)
    - Comision Permanente de Derechos Humanos. Reports, case studies, correspondence (with Nicaraguan government officials and others), statutes, treaty texts, speeches and statements, testimony, declarations, circulars, flyers, clippings, pamphlets, and newsletters, 1979-1989 (Folder 5-6)
    - Comision Permanente de Derechos Humanos (Box 7, Folder 1-2)
  - Indigenous populations. Reports, serial issue, letters to editors, pamphlet, printed articles, open letter to Ronald Reagan, and clippings relating to the Atlantic Coast area and the Miskito, Sumo, and Rama Indians, c. 1979-1987 (Folder 3)
  - Military. Planning document issued by the Nicaraguan Defense Ministry, 1985 (Folder 4)
  - Movimiento de Accion Popular-Marxista-Leninista. Policy statements, flyer, circulars, election material, biographical material, press releases, and bulletins, 1984 (Folder 5)
  - Opposition parties in exile. Newsletters, circulars, policy statements, speeches, clippings, pamphlets, reports, letters, and ephemera; includes the Alianza Revolucionaria Democratica, Bloque Opositor del Sur, Unidad Nicaraguense Opositora, Fuerzas Democraticas Nicaraguenses, and Resistencia Nicaraguense, 1983-1990 (Folder 6)
  - Opposition parties in exile (Box 8, Folder 1-2)
  - Partido Comunista de Nicaragua. Policy statements, election material, and ephemera, 1982-1987 (Folder 3)
  - Partido Conservador Democrata. Policy statements and election material, 1982-1984 (Folder 4)
  - Partido Conservador de Nicaragua. Bulletin, policy statement, and reports, 1985-1987 (Folder 5)
  - Partido Liberal Independiente. Program statement, resolutions, circular, clipping, and a pamphlet, 1984-1988 (Folder 6)
  - Partido Popular Social Cristiano. Policy statements, speech, and interview, 1984-1988 (Folder 7)
  - Partido Social Cristiano Nicaraguense. Reports, speeches, program statements, circular, declaration, meeting material, and a pamphlet, 1981-1989 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Partido Social Democrata. Policy statements, flyers, leaflets, and bulletins, 1986-1987 (Folder 2)
  - Partido Socialista Nicaraguense. Newsletters, policy statements, report, clipping, and election material, 1979-1984. SEE ALSO: OVERSIZE FILE (Folder 3)
  - Religion. Newsletters, pamphlets, and leaflets, 1981-1988 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - United States. Analyses of political conditions and relations with United States by United States governmnet agencies, Senate Committe on Foreign Relations and independent policy organizations. Newsletters, reports, pamphlet, speech, and flyer, 1979-1992. SEE ALSO: OVERSIZE FILE (Folder 2-3)
- OVERSIZE FILE, 1979-1990.
  - Election material, newsletters, poem, calendars, oversize pamphlet, flyers, and a stamp (Box 11)
- AUDIOVISUAL FILE, 1986-1989
  - Videotapes relating to opposition activities
    - Newsreels from Unidad Nicaraguense Opositora (UNO) 1986-1987 (Box 12, Videotapes 1-8)
      Use copy reference number: 89002_v_0003220
    - "Declaraciones de Roger Miranda Bengochea" newsreel undated (Videotape 9)
      Use copy reference number: 89002_v_0003221
    - "Noticias Internacionales Mas Importantes" newsreel 1989 (Videotape 10)
      Use copy reference number: 89002_v_0003225
  - Phonorecords (Record-cabinet Record cabinet)
    - "Un Son Para Mi Pueblo - Songs from the New Nicaragua," performed by Luis Enrique Mejia Godoy and Grupo Mancotal, 1983 (Folder 1)
    - "Cantos de un Pueblo que Lucha por su Libertad," performed by Grupo Libertad, 1986 (Folder 2)
- INCREMENTAL MATERIALS (Box 13-14)
  This addition to the collection has not yet been described. Please let the Hoover Institution Archives know if you would like to see this material described.